Dewey Brooke

Website: https://www.deweybrooke.org/

My name is Dewey Brooke, and I am a sixth generation Montanan from a small town of 120 called Pony. I enrolled at Montana State University in 2008 and graduated in 2012. From 2009 through 2013, I worked in the lab Dr. Brian Bothner. During that time I gained extensive experience in a wide-range of chemical and biochemical analytical equipment and techniques including LCMS, fluorescence, and electron microscopy. From 2013 to 2015, I further developed those techniques in addition to learning others while working in the lab of Dr. Peter Prevelige at the University of Alabama Birmingham. I have been exposed to a wide variety topics with a majority of my research focusing on the biochemical and biophysical characteristics of viruses. While at Montana State University, I studied the phospholipase a2 domain of adenoassociated virus, the assembly of hepatitis-b virus, and the maturation of nudaurelia capensis omega virus. At UAB, I studied the interaction between TRIM5a and HIV in hopes to better understand the mechanism of TRIM5a-mediated disassembly of HIV. Currently, I am enrolled in the Medical-Scientist Training Program at the University of Alabama School of Medicine.

Education

B.S., Biochemistry with the Highest Honors, Montana State University

May 4, 2012

Scholarships

- Lewis McRoberts Scholarship | Fall 2011-Spring 2012
- E Max & Ione Parkin Memorial Scholarship | Fall 2010-Spring 2011
- Asbjornson University Scholarship | Spring 2009-Spring 2012
- Governor's Merit Scholarship | Fall 2008-Spring 2012

Fellowships

- McNair Scholar | Spring 2010-Spring 2012
- INBRE Research Internship | Summer 2010-Spring 2012

Analytical Skills and Techniques

Mass Spectrometry

ESI-Mass-Spectrometry

(Bruker MicroTOF, Waters QTOF Premier Agilent 6520, and Agilent 6538)

MALDI-Mass-Spectrometry

(Bruker Autoflex III MALDI TOF)

Hydrogen-Deuterium Exchange

Whole-Protein Hydrogen-Deuterium Exchange LC-MS Method Development/Enzymatic Assay Development

Fluorescence Spectroscopy

Use of standard fluorescence instrumentation for analysis of proteins and small molecules (Varian Cary Eclipse Fluorescence Spectrophotometer)

QPCR-based differential thermodynamic profiling of proteins

Pyrene fluorescence of phospholipid bilayer fluidity Tryptophan Quenching

Programming

Google Cloud (R-Studio Server, BigQuery)

Julia

Python

R

SQL (Legacy and Standard)

Single and Multi-dimensional Chromatography

HPLC: Agilent 1100, Agilent 1200, LC Packings Ultimate

UPLC: Agilent 1290 FPLC: GE Akta FPLC

Size-Exclusion Chromatography Reverse Phase Chromatography

Hydrophyllic Interaction Chromatography

Ion-Exchange Chromatography

General

Transmission Electron Microscopy (Leo 906E)

Flow-Cytometry (BD FACSCalibur, AMNIS ImageStream)

Liposome preparation: Extrusion and Sonication

Column Packing and Immobilization

Western Blot

SDS-PAGE: Silver Staining, Sypro-Ruby, and Coomassie

QPCR

Software

Agilent Chemstation & Quantitative Analysis Bruker Hystar and Data Analysis

HDExaminer

MassLynx 4.1 & ProteinLynx Global Server

Lab Rotations

Akinyemi Ojesina M.D., Ph.D. Markus Bredel (Department of Radiation and Oncology) Dan Gorelick (Department of Pharmacology) Summer 2017 Summer 2016 Summer 2015

Research Experience

Research Assistant (Dr. Peter Prevelige; University of Alabama Birmingham)

June 2013- April 2015

- HDX Mass-Spectrometry on Viral Proteins
 - Acid induced conformational changes of P22 Tailspike
 - o Structural Transitions of the P22 Barrel Domain
 - o TRIM5a recognition of the HIV capsid
 - o TRIMCyp recognition of the HIV Capsid
 - HIV-2 virulence factor VPX/DCAF1/DDB1 Complex
- Identification of the Alternate Amino Acids Inserted During Suppression of the CFTR-G542X Nonsense Mutation

Research Assistant Grade III (Dr. Brian Bothner; Montana State University)

August 2012- April 2013

- Biophysical and biochemical characterization of receptor binding in parvoviruses
- The role of dynamics in the assembly of viral capsids using HDX mass-spectrometry
- Electron microscopy of phospholipase a2 induced tubule formation

Research Assistant Grade II (Dr. Brian Bothner; Montana State University)

May-August 2012

- Biophysical and biochemical characterization of adeno-associated virus
- The role of dynamics in the assembly of viral capsids using HDX mass-spectrometry
- Development of a pyrene-based fluorescent assay for monitoring membrane fluidity

Undergraduate Research Assistant (Dr. Brian Bothner; Montana State University) December 2009-May 2012

- Development of a fast liquid-chromatography/mass -spectrometry based lipase assay
- Applications of differential scanning fluorimetry for calculating thermodynamic parameters
- Development of single amino-acid resolution HDX mass-spectrometry
- Calculating the thermodynamics of proteins using chemical denaturation and tryptophan quenching

Publications

Cherwa JE Jr, Tyson J, Bedwell GJ, Brooke D, Edwards AG, Dokland T, Prevelige PE, Fane BA. (2016). **φX174 Procapsid Assembly: Effects of an Inhibitory External Scaffolding Protein and Resistant Coat Proteins In Vitro**. Journal of Virology

Bhardwaj, A., Sankhala, R. S., Olia, A. S., Brooke, D., Casjens, S. R., Taylor, D. J., ... Cingolani, G. (2016). **Structural Plasticity of the Protein Plug That Traps Newly Packaged Genomes in Podoviridae Virions.** The Journal of Biological Chemistry

Chang, B. J., Samal, A. B., Vlach, J., Fernandez, T. F., Brooke, D., Prevelige, P. E., & Saad, J. S. (2016). **Identification of the Calmodulin-Binding Domains of Fas Death Receptor.** PloS One, 11(1), e0146493.

Brooke, D., Movahed, N., & Bothner, B. (2015). **Universal buffers for use in biochemistry and biophysical experiments**. AIMS Biophysics, 2(3), 336–342.

Rayaprolu, V., Kruse, S., Kant, R., Movahed, N., Brooke, D. and Bothner, B. (2014). **Fluorometric Estimation of Viral Thermal Stability.** Bio-protocol 4(15): e1199. http://www.bio-protocol.org/e1199

Rayaprolu, V., Kruse, S., Kant, R., Venkatakrishnan, B., Movahed, N., Brooke, D., ... Bothner, B. (2013). **Comparative Analysis of Adeno-Associated Virus Capsid Stability and Dynamics**. Journal of Virology, 13150-13160.

Awards, Honors, and Features

- Phi Kappa Phi Outstanding Senior Award
- Lewis H. McRoberts Award: Outstanding Junior in Biochemistry
- Student Travel Award: 4th Biennial NISBRE Conference
- 1st place McNair Oral Presenter at the 2011 MSU Research Celebration
- Dean's List Fall 2008, Fall 2009-Spring 2012
- The National Society of Collegiate Scholars
- Featured in the Montana State University recruitment letter
- Featured in the 2012 MSU Campus Student Showcase
- Featured in an article by the Bozeman Daily Chronicle to represent the 2600 graduating seniors
- Featured in Mountains and Minds magazine in an article titled: The Heart of Montana
- Representative for the Honors Program at Montana State University

Presentations

UAB Structural Biology symposium; Poster

October 2014

Hydrogen/Deuterium Exchange Studies of TRIM Family Proteins

Dewey Brooke₁, Brady Summers₂, Yong Xiong₂, Jinwoo Ahn₃, Peter Prevelige₁

¹Department of Microbiology, University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham AL.

²Department of Molecular Biophysics and Biochemistry, Yale University, New Haven CT.

3Department of Structural Biology, University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine, Pittsburgh PA.

North American Cystic Fibrosis Conference; Poster

October 2014

Identification and Functional Consequences of the Alternate Amino Acids Inserted During Suppression of the CFTR-G542X Nonsense Mutation.

Xiaojiao Xue1, 3, Dewey Brooke2, Peter Prevelige2 David M. Bedwell1, 2, 3

1Department of Genetics, University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham AL.

²Department of Microbiology, University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham AL.

3Gregory Fleming James Cystic Fibrosis Research Center, University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, AL

Structural Biology Related to HIV/AIDS 2014; Poster

October 2014

Hydrogen/Deuterium Exchange Studies of TRIM Family Proteins

Dewey Brooke₁, Brady Summers₂, Yong Xiong₂, Jinwoo Ahn₃, Peter Prevelige₁

1Department of Microbiology, University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham AL.

²Department of Molecular Biophysics and Biochemistry, Yale University, New Haven CT.

3Department of Structural Biology, University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine, Pittsburgh PA.

4th Biennial NISBRE Conference; Poster

June 25-27, 2012

Monitoring the effects of pH and receptor binding on phospholipase activity in adeno-associated virus particles

Dewey Brooke₁, Navid Movahed₁, Antonette Bennett₂, Mavis Agbandje-McKenna₂, Brian Bothner₁

3. Chemistry & Biochemistry Department, Montana State University

²Biochemistry & Molecular Biology Department, University of Florida College of Medicine

FASEB 2012: Virus Structure and Assembly; Poster

June 10-15, 2012

Aging Gracefully; Maturation of a Tetravirus

Navid Movahed₁, Vamseedhar Rayaprolu₁, Jesse Ruzicka₁, Ravi Kant₁, Dewey Brooke₁, An Nguyen₁, Tatiana Domitrovic₂, Erhan Keles₁, John E. Johnson₂, Brian Bothner₁

1Chemistry & Biochemistry Department, Montana State University

2Scrips Research Institute, La Jolla, California

FASEB 2012: Virus Structure and Assembly; Poster

June 10-15, 2012

High Resolution Hydrogen/Deuterium Exchange Mass Spectrometry Gives Insight to the Mechanism of Action of Hepatitis B Virus Capsid Assembly Effectors

Navid Movahed₁, Dewey Brooke₁, Adam Zlotnick₂, Brian Bothner₁

1Chemistry & Biochemistry Department, Montana State University

2Department of Biology, Indiana University

Montana State University Research Celebration; Poster

April 19, 2012

Analysis of phospholipase activity in adeno-associated virus particles using liquid-chromatography/mass-spectrometry

Dewey Brooke1, Navid Movahed1, Mavis Agbandje-McKenna2, Brian Bothner1

Chemistry & Biochemistry Department, Montana State University

 ${}_2\text{Biochemistry}\ \&\ \text{Molecular}\ \text{Biology}\ \text{Department, University of Florida College of Medicine}$

American Society of Mass Spectrometry: Mass Spectrometry in Structural Biology; Poster

January 10-15, 2012

High Resolution Hydrogen/Deuterium Exchange Mass Spectrometry Gives Insight to the Mechanism of Action of Hepatitis B Virus Capsid Assembly Effectors

Navid Movahed₁, Dewey Brooke₁, Vamseedhar Rayaprolu₁, Adam Zlotnick₂, Brian Bothner₁

1Chemistry & Biochemistry Department, Montana State University

2Department of Biology, Indiana University

2nd Annual Montana State University McNair Research Symposium; Poster

December 8, 2011

Analysis of phospholipase activity in adeno-associated virus particles using liquid-chromatography/mass-spectrometry

Dewey Brooke1, Navid Movahed1, Mavis Agbandje-McKenna2, Brian Bothner1

¹Chemistry & Biochemistry Department, Montana State University

²Biochemistry & Molecular Biology Department, University of Florida College of Medicine

UC Berkeley McNair Symposium; Platform

August 4-7, 2011

Analysis of phospholipase activity in adeno-associated virus particles using liquid-chromatography/mass-spectrometry

Dewey Brooke1, Navid Movahed1, Mavis Agbandje-McKenna2, Brian Bothner1

.Chemistry & Biochemistry Department, Montana State University

²Biochemistry & Molecular Biology Department, University of Florida College of Medicine

59th Meeting of the American Society of Mass Spectrometry; Platform

April 27, 2011

Structure to Function: Use of Limited Proteolysis and Hydrogen Exchange Mass Spectrometry to Understand Virus Capsid Assembly and Cell Entry

Brian Bothner₁, Navid Movahed₁, Vamseedhar Rayaprolu₁, Jonathan Hilmer₁, Dewey Brooke₁, Adam Zlotnick₂, Mavis Agbandje-McKenna₃

¹Chemistry & Biochemistry Department, Montana State University

2Department of Biology, Indiana University

³Biochemistry & Molecular Biology Department, University of Florida College of Medicine

Montana State University Research Celebration; Platform and Poster

April 27, 2011

Analysis of phospholipase activity in adeno-associated virus particles using liquid-chromatography/mass-spectrometry

Dewey Brooke₁, Navid Movahed₁, Brad Poore₁, Mavis Agbandje-McKenna₂, Brian Bothner₁

¹Chemistry & Biochemistry Department, Montana State University

²Biochemistry & Molecular Biology Department, University of Florida College of Medicine

1st Annual Montana State University McNair Research Symposium; Poster

November 30. 2010

Analysis of phospholipase activity in adeno-associated virus particles using liquid-chromatography/mass-spectrometry

Dewey Brooke₁, Navid Movahed₁, Brad Poore₁, Mavis Agbandje-McKenna₂, Brian Bothner₁

Chemistry & Biochemistry Department, Montana State University

²Biochemistry & Molecular Biology Department, University of Florida College of Medicine

Montana State University Undergraduate Scholars Program Conference; Poster

August 6, 2010

Analysis of phospholipase activity in adeno-associated virus particles using liquid-chromatography/mass-spectrometry

Dewey Brooke1, Navid Movahed1, Brad Poore1, Mavis Agbandje-McKenna2, Brian Bothner1

Chemistry & Biochemistry Department, Montana State University

²Biochemistry & Molecular Biology Department, University of Florida College of Medicine

24th Annual Symposium of the Protein Society; Poster

August 1-5, 2010

Analysis of phospholipase activity in adeno-associated virus particles using liquid-chromatography/mass-spectrometry

Dewey Brooke₁, Navid Movahed₁, Brad Poore₁, Mavis Agbandje-McKenna₂, Brian Bothner₁

:Chemistry & Biochemistry Department, Montana State University

²Biochemistry & Molecular Biology Department, University of Florida College of Medicine

References

Brian Bothner Ph.D., Montana State University;

(406) 994-5270

Associate Professor of Biochemistry/Director of the Mass Spectrometry Facility

Peter Prevelige Ph.D., University of Alabama Birmingham

(205) 975-5327

Professor of Microbiology/Associate Professor of Biochemistry & Molecular Genetics

Trevor Douglas Ph.D. Indiana University;

(406) 994-6566

Earl Blough Professor of Chemistry